<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- feature.xml - Eclipse feature manifest
     Project OrcEclipseFeature

     Copyright (c) 2018 The University of Texas at Austin. All rights reserved.

     Use and redistribution of this file is governed by the license terms at
     URL: http://orc.csres.utexas.edu/license.shtml .
  -->
<feature
      id="edu.utexas.cs.orc.orceclipse"
      label="Orc Eclipse plug-in"
      version="2.1.1.qualifier"
      provider-name="The University of Texas at Austin"
      plugin="edu.utexas.cs.orc.orceclipse">

   <description url="https://orc.csres.utexas.edu/">
      The Orc programming language plug-in for the Eclipse IDE (Integrated
Development Environment). Provides editing, parsing, building, and execution services for the Orc programming language in Eclipse. Orc is a structured concurrent programming language.
   </description>

   <copyright url="http://orc.csres.utexas.edu/license.shtml">
      Copyright (c) 2018 The University of Texas at Austin. All rights
reserved.
   </copyright>

   <license url="http://orc.csres.utexas.edu/license.shtml">
      Orc License [An instance of the OSI Simplified BSD License]
--
Copyright (c) 2018 The University of Texas at Austin. All rights
reserved.
--
Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions
are met:
* Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
* Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer
in the documentation and/or other materials provided with the
distribution.
* Neither the name of the University of Texas at Austin nor the
names of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products
derived from this software without specific prior written permission.
--
THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN
&apos;&apos;AS IS&apos;&apos; AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT
NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT
SHALL THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT,
INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
(INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS
OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION)
HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT,
STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE)
ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED
OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
   </license>

   <url>
      <update label="Orc programming language" url="https://orc.csres.utexas.edu/eclipse_updates/"/>
   </url>

   <requires>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.ui" version="3.3.0" match="greaterOrEqual"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.core.runtime" version="3.3.0" match="greaterOrEqual"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.core.resources"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.debug.ui"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.team.core"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.help"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.ui.intro"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.ui.ide"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.ui.navigator"/>
      <import plugin="com.ibm.icu"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.core.variables"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.debug.core"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.jdt.core"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.jdt.debug.ui"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.jdt.launching"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.jface.text"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.ui.console"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.ui.editors"/>
   </requires>

   <plugin
         id="edu.utexas.cs.orc.orceclipse"
         download-size="187"
         install-size="187"
         version="0.0.0"
         unpack="false"/>

</feature>
