<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ref.sites.java.xml - DocBook source for an Orc reference manual section

     Copyright (c) 2011 The University of Texas at Austin. All rights reserved.

     Use and redistribution of this file is governed by the license terms in
     the LICENSE file found in the project's top-level directory and also found at
     URL: http://orc.csres.utexas.edu/license.shtml .
  -->

<section xml:id="ref.sites.java" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<title>Java sites</title>

<para>
Essential to Orc's role as an orchestration language is Orc's interaction with its host platform,
which in this implementation is the Java virtual machine (JVM).
In addition to calling Orc sites <foreignphrase>per se</foreignphrase>, Orc programs can access
arbitrary <indexterm><primary>Java</primary></indexterm>Java classes using the <indexterm><primary>class</primary></indexterm><code>import class</code> declaration.
Values in Java fields, values returned from Java methods, and values returned from Java constructors
may be used in Orc programs just as any other Orc value.
</para>


<section xml:id="ref.sites.java.classes">
<title>Java classes</title>

<para>
Java classes are named in an Orc program using the <code>import class</code> declaration.
In the scope of such a declaration, the declared name is bound to a value that acts as a proxy for the Java class.
This class proxy may be called as an Orc site, which invokes the Java class constructor corresponding to the arguments of the <link linkend="ref.expressions.call.site">site call</link>.
The class proxy also presents the class static methods and class static fields in the same manner as
an Orc <link linkend="ref.data.record">record</link>, with keys corresponding to the Java class members' names.
Class <indexterm><primary>method</primary></indexterm>methods appear as record elements that are sites, and are invoked by projecting the record element
using the <indexterm><primary>dot</primary></indexterm>dot notation and calling the site.
Fields appear as record elements that are <link linkend="ref.stdlib.state.Ref">references</link>, and are accessed and assigned
by projecting the record element using the dot notation and
using Orc's <code>?</code> and <code>:=</code> operators.
</para>

<para>
Note that Java allows fields and methods with identical names to be members of the same class.
In this case, Orc's Java class proxy resolves from the usage of a record element
whether to access the field or method.
</para>

<para>
Orc Java class proxies are not true Orc record values, although they appear syntactically as if they are.
</para>

<para>
Java classes are loaded from the Orc site classpath, which may be specified as a setting of the Orc
runtime engine; for example via a command-line option or an Eclipse project property.
If the class is not found on the Orc site
classpath, the loading attempt continues using the normal Java classpath.
</para>

</section>


<section xml:id="ref.sites.java.objects">
<title>Java objects</title>

<para>
Java objects may be returned by any Orc site call, including constructor or class static method
invocations of an Orc Java class proxy.
Java objects' methods and fields appear in the same manner as
an Orc record with keys corresponding to the members' names.
Methods appear as record elements that are sites, and are invoked by projecting the record element
using the dot notation and calling the site.
<indexterm><primary>field</primary></indexterm>Fields appear as record elements that are references, and are accessed and assigned
by projecting the record element using the dot notation and
using Orc's <code>?</code> and <code>:=</code> operators.
If a Java object is called as a site without projecting a member, the method name <link linkend="ref.data.record.specialkeys"><code>apply</code></link> is implicitly used.
</para>

<para>
Note that Java allows fields and methods with identical names to be members of the same class.
In this case, Orc's Java object proxy attempts to resolve from the usage of a record element
whether to access the field or method.
</para>

<para>
If a field's value is a class with a member named <code>read</code> this member will be
invoked when an Orc program accesses that field with the <code>?</code> operator.
Similarly, if a field's value is a class with a member named <code>write</code>, this member will be
invoked when an Orc program assigns a new value to that field with the <code>:=</code> operator.
Note that this is a potentially surprising name conflict.
</para>

</section>


<section xml:id="ref.sites.java.conversion">
<title>Java value conversions</title>

<para>
When interacting with Java classes and objects, Orc performs some conversions of values passed to and from the Java code.
Specifically, Orc applies conversions to the following:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Arguments of invoked constructors and methods</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Return values of invoked constructors and methods</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Accessed values from fields</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Assigned values to fields</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Accessed values from array components</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Assigned values to array components</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
The conversions applied are the following:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><code language="java">void</code> Java methods return <code>signal</code> in Orc.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Orc <link linkend="ref.data.numeric">integers</link> are converted to Java <code language="java">Byte</code>, <code language="java">Short</code>, <code language="java">Integer</code>, <code language="java">Long</code>, <code language="java">Float</code>, or <code language="java">Double</code>, as needed.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Orc <link linkend="ref.data.numeric">numbers</link> are converted to Java <code language="java">Float</code> or <code language="java">Double</code>, as needed.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Java <code language="java">Byte</code>, <code language="java">Short</code>, <code language="java">Integer</code>, and <code language="java">Long</code> are converted to Orc integers.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Java <code language="java">Float</code> and <code language="java">Double</code> are converted to Orc numbers.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Java primitive values are boxed and unboxed as needed, per <citetitle pubwork="book" xlink:href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/specs/jls/se5.0/html/conversions.html#5.1.7">The Java Language Specification</citetitle> ยง5.1.7 and ยง5.1.8.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Java widening primitive conversions are applied as needed, per <citetitle pubwork="book" xlink:href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/specs/jls/se5.0/html/conversions.html#5.1.2">The Java Language Specification</citetitle> ยง5.1.2.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
Note that Orc integers and numbers represent a larger range of values than the standard Java numeric types.
If an integer conversion is applied to an out-of-range value, the result is the least significant bits of the out-of-range value.
This will change the magnitude of the number and may change its sign.
If a floating-point conversion is applied to an out-of-range value, the result is positive or negative infinity, as appropriate.
</para>

</section>


<section xml:id="ref.sites.java.overloading">
<title>Java method and constructor invocation</title>

<para>
Orc invokes a Java method or constructor by closely approximating the Java method
invocation rules specified in <citetitle pubwork="book" xlink:href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/specs/jls/se5.0/html/expressions.html#15.12">The Java Language Specification</citetitle> ยง15.12.
This is only an approximation, because Orc performs Java compile-time steps at
run time using Java's reflection facilities, and therefore has a different
view of the types of values than the Java compiler.
However, in most cases, this difference has no effect.
At present, Orc does not recognize Java variable arity methods.
(In practice, this is a very rarely used feature of Java.)
</para>

<para>
Orc has a Java stack trace option, which may be specified as a setting to the Orc
runtime engine (for example, via a command-line option or an Eclipse run configuration setting).
This may be helpful when debugging Java invocations.
</para>

</section>


<section xml:id="ref.sites.java.array">
<title>Java arrays</title>

<para>
Java arrays are accessible in Orc.
To refer to a component of a Java array, follow the array value with a
nonnegative integer-valued expression in parenthesis.
Java arrays are zero-origin.
Array components appear as references in Orc.
Their values may be accessed and assigned using Orc's <code>?</code> and <code>:=</code> operators.
The Java <code language="java">length</code> pseudo-field of arrays is available in Orc as <code>length?</code>.
</para>

</section>


<section xml:id="ref.sites.java.examples">
<title>Examples</title>

<example xml:id="ref.sites.java.examples.constructinvoke">
<title>Construct a Java object, and invoke methods</title>
<programlisting language="orc-demo"><![CDATA[
{- Name a Java class and use it to invoke object methods -}
import class URL = "java.net.URL"

{- Create an instance-}
val googleUrl = URL("http://www.google.com/")

{- Invoke some methods -}
googleUrl.openConnection().getResponseMessage()

{-
OUTPUT:
"OK"
-}
]]></programlisting>
</example>

<example xml:id="ref.sites.java.examples.static">
<title>Accessing class members</title>
<programlisting language="orc-demo"><![CDATA[
{- Access Java's String and Boolean classes -}

import class JavaBoolean = "java.lang.Boolean"
import class JavaString = "java.lang.String"

-- Static field access
JavaBoolean.TRUE? |

-- Constructor invocation
JavaBoolean("true") |

-- Static method access
JavaBoolean.parseBoolean("true") |

-- Overloading and Orc-Java conversion -- String.valueOf(double) is invoked
JavaString.valueOf(2e108)

{-
OUTPUT:PERMUTABLE
true
true
true
"2E+108"
-}
]]></programlisting>
</example>

<example xml:id="ref.sites.java.examples.noarg">
<title>No-arg constructor invocation, field assignment, and field dereference</title>
<programlisting language="orc-demo"><![CDATA[
{- Constructor invocation -} 

import class FieldTestClass = "org.omg.CORBA.portable.ServantObject"

-- No-arg constructor invocation
FieldTestClass() >testInstance>

-- Field assignment
testInstance.servant := "test 4" >>

-- Field derefence
testInstance.servant?

{-
OUTPUT:
"test 4"
-}
]]></programlisting>
</example>

<example xml:id="ref.sites.java.examples.intoverflow">
<title>Integer conversion overflow</title>
<programlisting language="orc-demo"><![CDATA[
{- Demonstrate an Orc-to-Java integer conversion of an out-of-range value -}

import class JavaInteger = "java.lang.Integer"

val x = 1230000000000000000456789

JavaInteger.valueOf(x)

{-
OUTPUT:
-1530464171
-}
]]></programlisting>
</example>
		  
</section>


<section xml:id="ref.sites.java.links">
<title>Related Links</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<title>Related Reference Topics</title>
			<listitem><para><link linkend="ref.declarations.class"><code>import class</code> declaration</link></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><link linkend="ref.data.external">External data values</link></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><link linkend="ref.sites.custom">Custom sites</link></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><link linkend="ref.declarations.class.type">Interacting with Java Types</link></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<itemizedlist>
			<title>Related Tutorial Sections</title>
			<listitem><para><olink targetdoc="userguide" targetptr="ug.additional.import"><code>import class</code> declaration</olink></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
</section>

</section>
