<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ug.additional.import.xml - DocBook source for an Orc user guide section

     Copyright (c) 2011 The University of Texas at Austin. All rights reserved.

     Use and redistribution of this file is governed by the license terms in
     the LICENSE file found in the project's top-level directory and also found at
     URL: http://orc.csres.utexas.edu/license.shtml .
  -->
<section xml:id="ug.additional.import" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Importing Resources</title>

<para>
While the Orc language itself is expressive, 
and the <olink targetdoc="ref.stdlib" targetptr="ref.stdlib">Standard Library</olink> offers a number of useful sites and functions,
it is often necessary to extend the capabilities of a program by writing new sites,
using existing Java or Scala code,
or making use of Orc code written by other programmers.
Orc has three declarations, one corresponding to each of these three use cases.
</para>

<section xml:id="ug.additional.import.site">
<title>Writing Custom Sites</title>

<para>
The <code>import site</code> declaration allows a custom site to be imported
and used in an Orc program. There are specific requirements that must be met
by such sites; these are <olink targetdoc="ref.sites.custom" targetptr="ref.sites.custom">described in detail</olink> in the reference manual. 
</para>

<para>
Suppose one had written a custom site, implemented in the Java class <code language="java">my.example.site.ExampleSite</code>.
The following code would make it available as a site named <code>Example</code> in an Orc program:

<programlisting language="orc"><![CDATA[
import site Example = "my.example.site.ExampleSite"
]]></programlisting>
</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="ug.additional.import.class">
<title>Using Java Classes</title>
<para>
The <code>import class</code> declaration allows a Java class to be used as if
it were an Orc site. The class constructor is imported as a site, and calls to
that site return new Java objects whose methods and fields may be accessed using the dot
notation. The specific details of this conversion 
are <olink targetdoc="ref.sites.java" targetptr="ref.sites.java">documented</olink> in the reference manual. 
</para>

<para>
The following code imports and uses Java's <code language="java">File</code>,
<code language="java">FileReader</code>, and <code language="java">BufferedReader</code> classes
to read the first line of a text file.

<programlisting language="orc"><![CDATA[
import class File = "java.io.File"
import class FileReader = "java.io.FileReader"
import class BufferedReader = "java.io.BufferedReader"
val f = File("example.txt")
val reader = BufferedReader(FileReader(f))
reader.readLine()
]]></programlisting>
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="ug.additional.import.include">
<title>Including Source Files</title>

<para>
The <code>include</code> declaration reads a text file containing Orc declarations
and includes those declarations in the program as if they had occurred at the point
where the <code>include</code> declaration occurred. Any declarations may be included:
<code>val</code>, <code>def</code>, <code>import</code>, or even other <code>include</code>
declarations. This provides a primitive form of modularity, where Orc code shared
by many programs may be centralized in one or more include files.
</para>

<para>
An <code>include</code> declaration may name any URL, not just a local file. Thus,
useful include files can be shared over the Internet directly.
</para>

<para>
<programlisting language="orc-demo"><![CDATA[
{- Retrieve an include file from the Orc website and print the example message declared there -}

include "http://orc.csres.utexas.edu/documentation/example.inc"
Println(example_message)
]]></programlisting>
</para>

</section>


</section>
