<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ug.additional.datatypes.xml - DocBook source for an Orc user guide section

     Copyright (c) 2011 The University of Texas at Austin. All rights reserved.

     Use and redistribution of this file is governed by the license terms in
     the LICENSE file found in the project's top-level directory and also found at
     URL: http://orc.csres.utexas.edu/license.shtml .
  -->
<section xml:id="ug.additional.datatypes" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Datatypes</title>

<para>
We have seen Orc's predefined data structures: tuples, lists, and records. Orc also provides the capability
for programmers to define their own data structures, using a feature adopted from the ML/Haskell
language family called <firstterm>datatypes</firstterm> (also called variants or tagged sums).
</para>

<para>
Datatypes are defined using the <code>type</code> declaration:

<programlisting language="orc"><![CDATA[
type Tree = Node(_,_,_) | Empty()
]]></programlisting>

</para>

<para>
This declaration defines two new sites named <code>Node</code> and <code>Empty</code>.
<code>Node</code> takes three arguments, and publishes a <emphasis>tagged value</emphasis>
wrapping those arguments. <code>Empty</code> takes no arguments and does the same.
</para>

<para>
Once we have created these tagged values, we use a new pattern called a datatype pattern
to match them and unwrap the arguments:

<programlisting language="orc-demo"><![CDATA[
type Tree = Node(_,_,_) | Empty()
{- Build up a small binary tree -}
val l = Node(Empty(), 0, Empty())
val r = Node(Empty(), 2, Empty())
val t = Node(l,1,r)

{- And then match it to extract its contents -}
t >Node(l,j,r)>
l >Node(_,i,_)>
r >Node(_,k,_)>
( i | j | k )

{-
OUTPUT:PERMUTABLE
0
1
2
-}
]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
One pair of datatypes is so commonly used that it is already predefined in the standard library:
<code>Some(_)</code> and <code>None()</code>. These are used as return values for calls that
need to distinguish between successfully returning a value (<code>Some(v)</code>), and successfully
completing but having no meaningful value to return (<code>None()</code>). For example, a lookup
function might return <code>Some(result)</code> if it found a result, or return <code>None()</code>
if it successfully performed the lookup but found no suitable result.
</para>

</section>